Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Student Publication collection, 1890-1998 MVC0054.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Student Publications Collection
1890-2018
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0054.MS
3.00 Linear Feet 3 document boxes, 2 slim document box, 1 flat box
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 and a two year junior college was added in 1927. The Junior College remained open until 1969, when Mount Vernon College became a four-year unversity. The university was an independent institution until 1999, when it became affilated with The George Washington University. This collection includes student publications from Mount Vernon Seminary and College including: The Record, Asylum/Quintessence, Cellophane, Carousel, Mount Vernon College Bulletin, Mount Vernon Motif, Post Impressions, Mount Vernon College Front Page, The Voice, and other short run publications (Bluestocking, The Elephant's Ear, The Merri-Post, Newsense, Other than the White House, Post Script, and The College Republican).
Includes 3 document boxes, 1 slim document box, and one flat box.
Conditions Governing Access Note
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives were acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. The collection was transferred to the Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Biographical/Historical Note
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 with classes held at her residence on F Street; she named it after her brother's church in Baltimore, Mount Vernon Place Methodist. The Seminary began as a six year prepatory school, with four years of high school level classes, and two years of post-high school curriculum, calling it a "Family and Day School for Young Ladies." In order to graduate, students had to complete a formal process of "Senior Essays" in which they completed primary research and wrote on a current political or social topic, including such provocative issues as child labor, prohibition, poverty, and women's suffrage.
The school was moved to 1100 M. Street N.W. in 1900 and was once again moved in 1917 to a campus on Nebraska Avenue. In 1920 graduating class, eight women continued their education at universities such as the University of Wisconsin, Stanford, Northwestern and the University of Texas; by 1923 graduates were going to such other prestigious universities as UC-Berkeley, Columbia, Cornell, Smith College and the University of Chicago. Such advancements in higher education were uncommon for women of the day, but Mount Vernon was one of the premier prepatory institutions in the country.
In 1927, Mount Vernon established a Junior College, and with its establishment, students no longer had to complete six years of courses to receive a diploma; they graduated from the Seminary after four years and could continue on to the Junior College for two more years of college preparation. After World War II began, the U.S. Navy took over the campus in 1942 as a part of the war effort. During the 1943 academic year, the Seminary held classes in Spring Valley by leasing neighborhood residences. After receiving "just compensation" for their Nebraska Avneue campus, the school purchased 21 acres on Foxhall Road and surrounding areas in 1945, and had applied for accreditation to award Associates of Arts Degrees after completing two years of the Junior College.
Despite its expansion, by 1965 the Board of Trustees voted unanimously to dissolve the Seminary by 1969, as it could not financially support both institutions. During the 1960s, the Junior College developed new academic concentrations such as government, international relations and political science to reflect its location in the nation's capital. At the same time, it began to phase out its vocational training such as home economics and secretarial skills to make room for these higher education courses.
By 1973, the Board of Higher Education licensed the college to award Bachelor of Arts (BA) degrees such as Public Affairs, Government, Business Administration, Childhood, Special Education, and the Visual Arts, as well as honorary Doctor of Humane Letters and Juris Doctor Degrees; in 1976, the college received initial accreditation as a four-year college and was reaccredited ten years later. However, by 1996 the college announced a plan to affiliate with George Washington University and the last class of Mount Vernon College graduated in 1999. Today, as an affiliated campus of GWU, Mount Vernon offers special living accommodations, as well as learning and leadership programs for female students.
Arrangement Note
Organized into ten series: The Record, Asylum, Quintessence, Cellophane, Carousel, Mount Vernon College Bulletin, Mount Vernon Motif, Post Impressions, Mount Vernon College Front Page, The Voice, and Short Run Publications.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection contains student publications from Mount Vernon Seminary and Mount Vernon College, including literary magazines, newsletters, and newspapers. The material dates from 1890-1998.
Alumni & alumnae; Student publications; Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Students; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
- The Record, 1890-1899; Series 1; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  Arrangement Note
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series contains issues from The Record, dating from 1890 to 1899. A student publication from the Composition Department at Mount Vernon Seminary, the publication was distributed to students, parents, and alumnae for the annual subscription price of $1.00. The editor states the purpose of the publication as, "a medium through which all bits of news which are of interest to the various members of this large family may be transmitted, thus making it truly a 'record,' and so keep the daily life of the school before us. " Issues include poems, news (foreign, U.S.A., and Washington, D.C.), short stories, history articles, student life, personals, advertisements, commencements, events, honor rolls, births, deaths, marriages, school entertainments, household notes, faculty lists, and lists of boarding students.
  Alumni & alumnae; Student publications; Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Students; Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary
  - The Record, Vol. 1, No. 1-7 and Vol. 2, No. 1-7, November 1890-June 1892; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Record, Vol. 1, No. 6, April 1891; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Record, Vol. 1, No. 7, June 1891; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Record, Vol. 3, No. 1-7 and Vol. 4, No. 1-7, November 1892-May 1894; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Record, Vol. 5, No. 2, 5-6, and 8 and Vol. 6, No. 1-8, December 1894-June 1896; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Record, Vol. 7, No. 1-8 and Vol. 8, No. 1-6 and 8, November 1896-May 1898; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Record, Vol. 9, No. 1, November 1899; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Record, Cover Sheet, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Asylum/Quintessence, 1973-1980; Series 2; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  Scope and Contents
  The materials of this series include issues from Asylum and Quintessence. Asylum ranges in date from 1973-1980. Quintessence ranges in date from 1981-1985. A student literary magazine at Mount Vernon College, the publication was called Asylum until its name was officially changed to Quintessence in 1981.
  These issues contain poetry, essays, photography, fiction and painting by Mount Vernon students.
  The editor states the meaning behind the name Quintessence by writing, "Mount Vernon is on its fifth campus so quintet, which means five, and is a part of quintessence, was thought to be appropriate. Also, the definition of 'quintessence' is 'the essence of a thing in its purest and most concentrated form.' We felt this name would be fitting since we consider poetry a form of art in its purest form."
  Each issue of Quintessence contains poetry and photography from Mount Vernon students as well as entries from students from other colleges, universities, and high schools in the Washington, D.C. area submitted as part of the Mount Vernon College Poetry Festivals.
  When possible, two copies of each issue are included.
  Arrangement
  Women -- Education; Student publications; Alumni & alumnae; Students; Women's colleges; Mount Vernon College
  - Asylum, Vol. 1, Issue 1; Vol. 2 Issue 1-2; Vol. 3, Issue 1, 1973-1975; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Asylum, Vol. 4-5, 1975-1977; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Asylum, Vol. 6-7, 1978-1979; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Asylum, Special Issue; Vol. 8, 1979-1980; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Quintessence, Vol. 1-3, 1981-1983; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Quintessence, Vol. 4-5, 1984-1985; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Cellophane, 1948-1961; Series 3; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  The materials of this series include issues of Cellophane.They range in date from 1948-1961. A student newsletter at Mount Vernon Seminary, Cellophane reported on events and everyday life on campus. Discussed topics include: upcoming events (dances, parties, student government elections, sporting evets, etc.), list of Honor Roll students, future plans for graduating seniors, sports scores, student polls, and campus gossip.
  Alumni & alumnae; Student publications; Students; Women's colleges; Women -- Education; Mount Vernon Seminary
  - Cellophane, 1948-1951, Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cellophane, 1951-1955, Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cellophane, 1956-1961, Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Carousel, 1950-1968; Series 4; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  The materials of this series include issues of Carousel. They range in date from 1950-1968. A student literary magazine at Mount Vernon Seminary, issues of Carousel contain short stories, non-fiction essays, poetry, and editorials by Mount Vernon students.
  Alumni & alumnae; Students; Student publications; Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Mount Vernon Seminary
  - Carousel, Vol.3, No. 2-3, Spring 1951 and Vol. IV, No. 1, 1950-1952; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Carousel, 1956, 1958, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Carousel, 1959, 1960, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Carousel, 1961, December 1961, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Carousel, March 1962, May 1962, December 1962, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Carousel, May 1963, December 1963, April 1963, Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Carousel, April 1964, Spring 1965, Autumn 1965, 1964-1965; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Carousel, December 1966, Spring 1966, Spring 1967, 1968, 1966-1968; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Mount Vernon College Bulletin, 1973-1981; Series 5; 1 Linear Feet 1 flat box
  The materials of this series include issues of Mount Vernon College Bulletin. They range in date from 1973-1981. A student newpaper at Mount Vernon College, issues of Mount Vernon College Bulletin contain articles about student/faculty/administration news as well as updates about alumnae and reports on important campus events. Some issues also contain articles regarding the history of the school.
  Women's colleges; Students; Women -- Education; Student publications; Alumni & alumnae; Mount Vernon College
  - Mount Vernon College Bulletin, 1973-1976, 1975-1976; Series 5 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Mount Vernon College Bulletin, 1977-1981, Series 5 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Mount Vernon Motif, 1988-1989; Series 6; 1 Linear Feet 1 flat box
  The materials of this series include issues of Mount Vernon Motif. They range in date from 1988-1989. A student newpaper at Mount Vernon College, issues of Mount Vernon Motif contain articles about student/faculty/administration news, reports on important campus events, horoscopes, world news, music editorials, and restaurant recommendations. Some issues also contain articles regarding the history of the school. When possible, two copies of each issue are included.
  Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Student publications; Students; Alumni & alumnae; Mount Vernon College
  - Mount Vernon Motif, 1988-1989, Series 6 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Post Impressions, 1982-1988; Series 7; 1 Linear Feet 1 flat box
  The materials of this series include issues of Post Impressions. They range in date from 1982-1988. A student newpaper at Mount Vernon College, issues of Post Impressions contain articles about student/faculty/administration news, reports on important campus events, recipes, classifieds, and letters to the editor.
  Alumni & alumnae; Students; Student publications; Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Mount Vernon College
  - Post Impressions, 1982-1985, Series 7 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Post Impressions, 1987-1988, Series 7 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Mount Vernon College Front Page, 1975; Series 8; 1 Linear Feet 1 flat box
  The materials of this series include issues of Mount Vernon College Front Page. They date from 1975. A student newpaper at Mount Vernon College, issues of Mount Vernon College Front Page contain articles about student/faculty/administration news, reports on important campus events, student polls, and editorials. Some issues also contain articles regarding the history of the school. When possible, two copies of each issue are included.
  - Mount Vernon College Front Page, 1975, Series 8 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- The Voice, 1990-1998; 1990-1994; Series 9; 1 Linear Feet 1 flat box
  The materials of this series include issues of The Voice. They date from 1990. A student newpaper at Mount Vernon College, issues of The Voice contain articles about student/faculty/administration news, reports on important campus events, information on issues pertinent to college students, and editorials. Some issues also contain articles regarding the history of the school.
  Alumni & alumnae; Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Students; Student publications; Mount Vernon College
  - The Voice, 1990, Series 9 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - The Voice, 1991-1992, Series 9 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Voice, 1993-1998, Series 9 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Short Run Publications, 1963-1992; 1963-1973; Series 10; 0.25 Linear Feet 1 slim document box
  The materials of this series include issues of various short run publications from Mount Vernon Seminary and College. They date from 1964-1992. These publications include literary magazines, political newsletters, and campus newsletters.
  Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Students; Student publications; Alumni & alumnae; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
  - Bluestocking, 1964-1965, undated; Series 10 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Elephant's Ear, 1965; Series 10 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Merri-Post, 1965, undated; Series 10 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Newsense, 1967-1968; Series 10 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Other than the White House, 1968; Series 10 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Post Script, 1972-1973; Series 10 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Bugs..., March 1983; Series 10 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The College Republican, 1992; Series 10 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Communicate-Her, Fall 1979; Series 10 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - aureate, 2015 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Arts and culture magazine, 2016-2018 (Box 6, Folder 2)